<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>CITF-Postdoc</title>
<link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 21:12:44 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Technical specs for this website</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-11-technical-specs.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’m using this website as a way to help organize and share key documents and resources. The research protocols are in flux at this stage in the project’s development, and this will make it easier to distribute up-to-date drafts with partners, while simultaneously enhancing transparency.</p>
<p>This post outlines the technical specifications for this website and outlines a roadmap for its further development. It will therefore be continually updated as the site evolves.</p>
<section id="fundamentals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fundamentals">Fundamentals</h2>
<p>This website is based on <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, a platform for writing and publishing scientific and technical writing. I had used quarto before but without fully understanding it, and now I am starting to see its elegance.</p>
<p>I had started off using Hugo, but there were too many limitations that Quarto was able to accomodate. You can find an older version of this post reflecting that setup here: <a href="https://github.com/zackbatist/CITF-Postdoc/commit/2346852df7224ca18eff65c0f34335cc6245a78a">#2346852</a>.</p>
<p>The site is hosted on GitHub Pages. The repo is located at <a href="https://github.com/zackbatist/CITF-Postdoc">https://github.com/zackbatist/CITF-Postdoc</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="generating-pdfs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="generating-pdfs">Generating PDFs</h2>
<p>As an avid user, one thing I really like about Quarto is the ability to generate PDFs alongside html versions served over the web. I started tinkering with includes but I need to review how Quarto passes info from YAML frontmatter. It is not at all straightforward and I will need to experiment a bit more with this to get the hang of it.</p>
</section>
<section id="archiving-and-version-control" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="archiving-and-version-control">Archiving and Version Control</h2>
<p>Every change is tracked using git. I would also like to archive each research protocol in Zenodo once they reach a point of stability. This would ensure that they ca be aassigned DOIs and detailed metadata, which will make them easier to reference.</p>
<p>However, I do not want to rely on Zenodo’s GitHub integration for two reasons: (1) I want this to be as platform-agnostic as possible, and (2) that system relies on GitHub’s release system which operates on the level of the whole repository rather than specific files.</p>
<p>I might be able to write a custom CI workflow to archive specific files to Zenodo using their API. But, I want to be able to toggle this option, rather than have it occur for every single detected change. Maybe I can accomplish this by pushing the changes that I want to archive to a dedicated branch that the CI workflow is configured to operate on. Or it might be easier to simply do this manually, since I’m not sure I will be using it that often anyway.</p>
</section>
<section id="git-submodules" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="git-submodules">Git Submodules</h2>
<p>Since I’m dealing with potentially sensitive information, including recordings, transcripts and notes deriving from interviews that participants may opt to keep confidential, I need to isolate those files so they remain private and secure. To accomplish this, I will set up private git repos on the MCHI-administered GitLab instance and integrate them into my main project repository (hosted on GitHub, and hence less secure) as submodules. I will then configure my quarto rendering options to ignore any subdirectories deemed sensitive enough to not share publicly (which may not include everything in the submodule). I intend to follow <a href="https://www.taniarascia.com/git-submodules-private-content/">this guide written by Tania Rascia</a> to pull this off.</p>
<p>Just as a quick reminder of the procedure for committing and syncing changes, based on my testing:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Make changes to files in the submodule.</li>
<li>Commit and sync those changes to the remote submodule.</li>
<li>Obtain a record of those changes from the remote submodule:
<ul>
<li><code>git submodule update --remote</code></li>
<li>This can be verified using <code>git status</code>; changes should be indicated as <code>(new commits)</code>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Commit the record of commits to the main repo’s remote.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="qc" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qc">qc</h2>
<p>I intend to use <a href="https://qualitative-coding.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html">qc</a>, a novel too for qualitative data analysis designed for qualitaitve thinking. It’s a command line tool that makes QDA compatible with <a href="https://plain-text.co/">textfile based social science workflows</a>, which more-or-less aligns with my overall approach. qc also plays nice with my plan to isolate potentially sensitive information on a private git submodule, and is loosely compatible with my strategy for posting memos and research outputs publicly via this website.</p>
<p>I’m also communicating with its maintainer, Chris Proctor, who is an education researcher and computer scientist based at SUNY Buffalo. This is the perfect combination for this kind of work since he specializes in instilling computational literacies, he has the technical chops to actually develop this system, and most of all: qualitative data analysis is the bread and butter of education research, so he is developing from an informed perspective. I really like what I see so far, and I’m eager to collect data of my own so that I can maximize the full potential that this system affords.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-11-technical-specs.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 21:12:44 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Week notes (2025-W08)</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W08.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Some highlights from this week:</p>
<ul>
<li>I met with Isabel for our biweekly update. We talked about challenges involved in introducing my work to epidemiologists, and practiced some techniques for communicating what my project is about.</li>
<li>I made some revisions to my ethics protocol in response to the feedback provided by the IRB. Currently trying to resolve a technical problem with the online portal that processes these applications.</li>
<li>I submitted a peer-review.</li>
<li>I followed up on some translation work for SNAP.</li>
<li>I continued with my methodology notes.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>week notes</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W08.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Week notes (2025-W07)</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W07.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This week I continued my methodological readings. Today I got some requests for minor modifications to my REB protocol, which will be rather painless to implement.</p>
<p>I also attended the Public Health day, a student conference where grad students presented their practicum research. I really enjoyed engaging with the students at the poster session, I actually learned quite a lot.</p>
<p>Next week I’ll try to round off my methodology readings in anticipation of my REB application being approved by the end of this month.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>week notes</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W07.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Week notes (2025-W06)</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W06.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This week was a bit slower than usual. The highlight was my meeting with Isabel to go over details about harmonization procedures and to discuss projects that may serve as potential cases. I got a better sense of the community composition and the kinds of challenges that are commonly experienced, and Isabel was able to provide me with contacts to get in touch with once I’m ready to begin collecting data.</p>
<p>I was less active with regards to my methodology notes this week, having spent much time re-organizing and consolidating them. I’m also reading about coding techniques and the foundational principles and debates surrounding grounded theory, but there is a lot of ground to cover and I’m taking it all in before I begin recording my thoughts in a systematic way.</p>
<p>I did some non-postdoc service this week too. I started a peer-review that I had committed to, participated in the monthly <a href="https://sslarch.github.io/">SSLA</a> meeting, and completed the first-pass screening of archaeology-related journals in the <a href="https://doaj.org/">Directory of Open Access Journals</a> to verify their inclusion in <a href="https://diamond.open-archaeo.info/">diamond.open-archaeo</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>week notes</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W06.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Week notes (2025-W05)</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W05.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The first part of my week largely involved reading and taking notes on methodological texts. I focused on case study design and qualitative coding techniques. I plan to continue my methodology readings on coding techniques, memoing, interview methods and systematic note-taking, as well filling in gaps in my understanding of grounded theory and related debates. These readings are especially useful in this planning stage, but also serve to fill time while I wait for my IRB approval.</p>
<p>On that note, I finally submitted my ethics application on Thursday. I expect an expedited review based on the low-risk nature of the work. I posted the materials I submitted on the <a href="../ethics-protocol.html">ethics protocol</a> page.</p>
<p>I had my biweekly meeting with David, and he was very encouraging.</p>
<p>I met with Isabel Fortier again yesterday and we came up a list of six projects that may serve as potential cases. We will discuss them in greater depth next week.</p>
<p>I finally sent some feedback on <a href="https://qualitative-coding.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">qc</a>.</p>
<p>Next week I also need to fulfill a few commitments not as related to the postdoc: I need to work on a peer-review I had committed to, continue assemmbling constructive feedback for qc, and continue <a href="https://github.com/open-archaeo/diamond.open-archaeo.info/issues/19">going through the DOAJ</a> for the <a href="https://diamond.open-archaeo.info/">diamond.open-archaeo</a> initiative.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>week notes</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W05.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Week notes (2025-W04)</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W04.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This week was a bit slower than last. I spent much of it finalizing the content for my IRB application, and the rest preparing for a meeting with a key stakeholder relating to my research.</p>
<p>The IRB application is more or less done, just waiting on David and the department head to sign off. It was a major opportunity to re-organize my research protocol and related documents. I shuffled some things over into various placeholder sections in my <a href="../notes/methodology-notes.html">methodology notes</a>, and pushed a revised <a href="../research-protocol.html">research protocol</a> to the website.</p>
<p>Yesterday I posted about <a href="https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2025-01-24-ai-in-my-work.html">on the role of AI in my research</a>. It’s mainly meant to lay out my current state of thinking on AI. I’m not fixed to those ideas, and I think there is much more nuance than I do justice to in that post, but putting it on the page helped me consolidate and put aside some scrambled opinions.</p>
<p>After playing around with <a href="https://qualitative-coding.readthedocs.io/">qc</a> on Sunday, I started to assemble some feedback. I may post a github issue later this week, once I’ve had a chance to consolidate and edit my thoughts.</p>
<p>I participated in the weekly CITF logistics update, after which I met with Aklil to discuss the overall strategy for her project and strategize on how we might form the focus groups for that work. We’re gonna meet more regularly, just to share some updates on our respective projects which have a lot in common.</p>
<p>On Thursday I met with Isabel Fortier, with the intention of discussing data harmonozation initiatives that might serve as potential cases. It was a bit of a tough meeting. During the first 45 minutes I struggled to communicate the purpose of my work, but I think by the end we reached a greater understanding of what this work will entail and the unique perspective it will bring. One surprising outcome that I still need to think through is Isabel’s suggestion that I slow down a bit, immerse myself more in the world of data harmonization. While she is absolutely right that I’ve been rushing through this first month, I do feel pressure to get the project going and to start accumulating data — I felt a similar pressure when starting my PhD, too. So I need to put my eagerness aside so that the data are relevant and of good enough quality. Isabel offered to schedule regular meetings with me, and even to have me work in the Maelstrom office once a week, and I’m extremely grateful for her support! Plus, I’ll get to have lunch with my mom who works in the same hospital complex, one building over :)</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>week notes</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W04.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On the role of AI in my research</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2025-01-24-ai-in-my-work.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>AI is upon is, and although I would probably be ok if it wasn’t around, I have been (and still am, to a certain extent) tempted to use it in my research. So here I’m gonna articulate some of my thoughts on AI. This isn’t written to convince anyone, or even to convince myself. Just to lay out all my thoughts and take stock of my preconceptions, disapointments, hopes and desires, etc.</p>
<p>Also, I’m gonna use AI, LLM and whatever other brand names and marketing buzzwords interchangably here. Draw whatever conclusions you want about that.</p>
<p>I see AI as being potentially useful in a few productive activities I regularly engage in:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Transcribing spoken words into written text</p>
<p>Transcription is a significant component of processing interview data, and this can be extremely slow work. It’s a lot easier to edit a transcript produced through a computer algorithm rather than start from scratch. I used trint, otter and other similar tools before all the AI hype, and more recently I’ve been using whisper to transcribe voice notes that I record while I’m waiting for the bus or drifting off to sleep. I’m not really sure how they’re much different, to be honest. Is AI just a rebrand of natural language processing in these contexts? Either way, I will most certainly be using some automatic transcrion tool in my research.</p></li>
<li><p>Summarizing, breaking down and simplifying complex bundles of ideas</p>
<p>I do a lot of reading, and it can be hard to get through everything on my list. I therefore make lots of compromises and refrain from reading some things because I just can’t make enough time to get through everything. I imagine that AI can help summarize some key points across a whole corpus of articles on my to-read pile, and I may try it out once I have time to figure out the right tooling for the job. However, I do gain a lot of value from the process of reading. Specifically, as a scholar of scientific practice, I’m interested in the language and rhetoric authors use to describe and situate their methods and findings, and I’m not sure if automatic summary tools can capture and communicate this nuance in ways that I want.</p></li>
<li><p>Generating code snippets for data processing and visualization</p>
<p>This is arguably the most productive potential application I can imagine. Specifically, I’m thinking about using this to generate R code that processes and visualizies data according to imagined outcomes. This is directly relevant to a project I’m working on where I’ve already finished the workflows for scraping and processing the data, I have the questions I want to ask of it, but I don’t have the practical know-how to generate the code that will allow me to address them. ggplot is just so dense to me, and stitching together code snippets from stack exchange is a major pain in the ass that produces a horrible abomination of code that would not pass the muster of any rigorous code review. What’s more, those queries to search stack exchange are already half-formed AI prompts! At least an AI would generate some harmony in the code, and I might learn something by having a tidy and consistent template.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I’m more ambivalent and critical about using AI in these contexts where it’s been really hyped:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Any form of writing, including generating emails and abstracts</p>
<p>For me, writing is a creative process and a way of unerstanding. It’s a mechanism through which I come to learn about something. The experience of drafting and revising a document is crucial to my research process. This is especially important for honing my position as a scholar at the intersection of various disciplinary communities, who have distinct language and modes of communication.</p></li>
<li><p>Querying for truth claims</p>
<p>To be clear, the idea that knowledge can be total, absolute and disembodied is deeply flawed, and the popular reception of AI as a neutral observer and reporter of nature makes me sad. That being said, I’m still ambivalent about the potential for specialized, home-grown LLMs as means of parsing, sorting through and obtaining greater value from under-used resources. There are patterns in even the messiest and least formal documents we create, and even if we can’t draw information <em>from</em> these documents, LLMs may be useful to help us reflect on the circumstances of their creation. I keep thinking about <a href="https://github.com/smgprojects/bots">Shawn Graham’s twitter bots</a> in this context (which were not based on AI, but whatever), which attempted to spit out segments of artificial reports and fieldwork drama, which real archaeologists often related and resonded to. These <em>responses</em> were interesting to me, often expressed as collective fascination, titilation or disgust, and reminiscient of the apprehension one might experience when hearing your own voice played back while standing at the opposite end of a long hallway. Reacting to distortions of your own experience from very different perspectives can be a really powerful reflexive exercise.</p></li>
<li><p>As a brainstorming tool, or as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging">rubber duck</a></p>
<p>I’ve heard about people using AI chatbots as agents to bounce their ideas off of. Kind of like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ELIZA">eliza</a>, but for productive work. While I think it’s intriguing, I don’t know where I’d start. Also, drawing up the prompt and figuring out how to ask the right questions may already be enough to get the ideas flowing. I think I already do this in some ways by drafting little ephemeral notes, usually directed toward a specific person or imaginary audience while anticipating their feedback. It also somehow seems like a perverse way to de-socialize work, and in a world where students and postdocs feel increasingly isolated, I’d much rather solicit and provide feedback among peers. This has been the foundation of some of my most solid friendships and professional partnerships, and should be encouraged.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I also have some previously-unstated opinions in relation to some common critiques of AI:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Process versus product</p>
<p>AI seems to be really good at devising formulaic outputs. That is, it’s good at getting things to look like things whose shapes are already well-defined. This can be valuable in various use cases, like writing emails according to a template or translating texts between languages. I could imagine it being really helpful for those who are coming into a field where certain skills are taken for granted, such as learning how to write “proper” academic emails as a student who is not fluent in english. Imagine being up against a deadline for a job application, while also being knee-deep in unpaid work to get your name out there; an LLM could be a godsend. So I don’t discount easy outputs as inherently bad. A standard output for one is a week-long struggle for another, so I think this distinction between product and process is a false and misleading dichotomy.</p></li>
<li><p>Bad instructions</p>
<p>Sometimes I find it really hard to believe that people could earnestly follow whatever an AI tells them. But I think we’re getting to the point of urban mythmaking, similar to the older wariness about following your GPS into a lake. There’s a story behind every warning sign, even if it’s a projection of <em>what you think might happen</em> if you disregard it.</p></li>
<li><p>“Intelligence”</p>
<p>One weird thing about AI branding is the smushing together of some unified idea of what constitutes “intelligence”. We’ve already been through this with “smart” gadgets, which have always just been ways to capture consumer products under a platforms proprietary injected plastic molds and information protocols. AI is literally just a way to sell you a new version of the smart gadget you threw out last year.</p></li>
<li><p>Truthiness, i.e., AI’s ability to sound authoritative while also making false claims</p>
<p>I cringe at any retort to a screenshot of AI giving a wrong definition of a thing. Accuracy of responses should come secondary to critique of the notion that all forms of knowledge can be presented in terms of absolute, disembodied and universally truths. For example, when people ridicule AI’s inability to identify the capitols of various nation states, I see missed opportunities to challenge the value of <em>any answer</em> that <em>anyone</em> might provide. True subversion would be to reject or re-frame the question and the simplicity with which it is addressed.</p>
<p>One another related note, I see a lot of weird parallels between myths about truth claims made by AI and by practitioners of qualitative data analysis (QDA) — and, as a qualitative researcher, this is obviously a bit unsettling. Specifically, in both QDA and AI, there is no <em>actual</em> attempt to make absolute truth claims, but the focus is rather on attempting to identify and draw out meaningful elements of elicitations in a corpus, and to trace patterns between them. In my current opinion, the key difference lies in positionality. Any QDA researcher who laim that their cases are representative of all experiences will be laughed out of the room. Meanwhile, AI is lauded for the claims made by their creators that it can derive unambiguous and concrete knowledge from inherently situated and biased data sources. Humility is key while contributing to collective knowledge bases, and AI risks changing the dynamic away from deriving greater value from constructive discourse and toward a system where the loudest voice in the room wins.</p></li>
<li><p>Climate change</p>
<p>AI uses a lot of energy, and is therefore said to be wasteful. However I think there are certain wasteful <em>components</em> of AI. For instance, generative models that spit out a full sentence to wrap around the answer to a question don’t have to do all that extra work. Also, not everyone is reliant on fossil fuels, and the critique that AI is <em>necessarily</em> bad for the environment is laden with a thick American accent (as is the case with so many of the loudest opinions on the internet).</p>
<p>That being said, there are enormous problems with resource allocation in AI, and I’m not trying to dismiss all concerns. I see these concerns as relating to the distribution of power and wealth in society at large, and AI is one aspect of this. Sometimes I wonder if comparisons can be made between using AI in selective research contexts and eating a burger or a banana, which each have their own environmental costs. <a href="https://manchesteruniversitypress.co.uk/9781526162632/">But thinking in this way is a bit of a trap.</a></p></li>
</ul>
<p>I also see that rhetoric, including anxieties about AI, differs in the various communities I participate in:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>In digital-x, where x = {archaeology | humanities | librarianship | whatever}</p>
<p>There’s a lot of experimentation going on. Honestly, I don’t know much about it and I tend to scroll past any discussion about AI applications in archaeology that appears in my feed. Part of me sees it as a passing trend, but it could be better framed as a wild frontier, as is the case with many other things in digital archaeology. People are still in the process of taming the landscape, to make it better suit their needs, and maybe I’ll join in once the settlement is established. But I’m not personally motivated by the dynamism of the current landscape, at least in this particular domain.</p></li>
<li><p>Epidemiology, biostats, public health</p>
<p>I’m still too new in this community to really make sense of this yet. I’ll continue to watch and learn and listen.</p></li>
<li><p>Broader social science and humanities, as well as libraries, archives and museums</p>
<p>Critique tends to follow broader, more abstract, and more common-sense lines of thought. In my view, much of this does not really account for the material problems and imperfections in which the social sciences and humanities operate. AI is a lifeline for many people in an overworked, overburdened, under-resourced and hyper-competitive environment, and tut-tutting around how other people use AI sometimes comes across as tone-deaf and disrespectful. Some criticisms of AI being used in real, practical circumstances make me second guess critics’ supposed commitments to improving the social experience of research. The fundamental problem is inequitable access to financial and material resources, and AI’s prevalence is a major symptom of, or — depending on your perspective — resolution to that. People’s who recognize this have no choice but to post broader and more abstract criticisms, which come across as somewhat hollow when disconnected from real and tangible experiences.</p></li>
<li><p>Senior faculty</p>
<p>Probably the most ambivalent of all communities are senior faculty, who want AI to be useful and will test the waters without fully committing. Which is fine and very prudent, and honestly I identify most with this perspective, despite my position as a lowly postdoc.</p></li>
<li><p>Grad students</p>
<p>I engage with many grad students. I share my workspace with grad students and encounter them constantly in my day to day neighbourhood forays, where I overhear and sometimes participate in conversations about AI. In my new work environment (Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Occupational Health), the grad students who I engage with have a relatively positive perception of AI. They seem to find greater value in the ability to automate complex processes, using it as a black box of sorts, with predictable and abstracted inputs and outputs, which they see as especially helpful for coding. Outside of this space I’m encountering way more diversity of thought on AI, and I’m not quite sure how to group these viewpoints to structure a proper reaction. I think this in fact contributes to the multitude of perspectives, since no one really cares that much one way or the other to really have a strong opinion (though I sense an overwhelming dissatisfaction when it comes to AI in consumer contexts; this post is largely about productive uses of AI in research and pedagogy).</p>
<p>I was also told about students learning RStats by just having AI generate their code. The person who pointed this out to me related this to the growing misconception that to learn stats you first need to learn how to code. This in turn relates to the sense that to learn how to do RStats, you just need to memorize a series of steps and copy the text from the slides into the IDE. So, in the end, AI reveals the inadequacy of the teaching mechanisms for programming and stats classes, similarly to how AI has revealed the inadequacy of essay-writing as a pedagogical technique.</p>
<p>On the other hand, some students are concerned about dulling their skills, or even not being able to take advantage of opportunities to learn new skills, due to the temptation to automate these tasks. Some upper-year PhD students are glad that they were trained in the fundamentals prior to the AI hype wave. This makes me wonder how students are determining what skills they think they need to know how to do on their own and what is worth running through an LLM. Does it basically operate as a bullshit sensor, where you can smell from a distance that the work is just gonna be tedium and irrelevant? Or is it more out of practical necessity, where you’re stretched so thin that you simply have to rely on these tools to achieve anything meaningful, almost as a mechanism for salvaging one’s work from the claws of austerity? In either case, this points to PhD programs’ inadequacy to match students’ needs and desires, and overwhelming amount of administravia or (seemingly) irrelevant work that students are made to do, which get in the way of their true interests.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Maybe I’ll have more to share some other time.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>AI / LLM</category>
  <category>Methods</category>
  <category>QDA</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2025-01-24-ai-in-my-work.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Week notes (2025-W03)</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W03.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’m trying out a new way to track and communicate my progress on this project. Every week I’ll write a post to track the work I’ve been doing and reflect on my activities. I’ll try to maintain this document throughout the week, tidy it up and post it here on Friday afternoons. However the specific process will probably vary as it grows into the rest of my workflow.</p>
<p>I’m purposefully trying to <strong>not</strong> tie this into the personal knowledge management trend. It’s for me and my own purposes, and I don’t want to get bogged down with the unabashed managerial phoniness that belies the PKM phenomenon.</p>
<p>Anyway, I didn’t take notes on my work this past week, but here’s an overview of what I’ve done from memory:</p>
<p>Continued to take <a href="../notes/maelstrom-readings.html">notes on readings produced by the Maelstrom Project and its partners</a>.</p>
<p>Continued to investigate and maintain <a href="../notes/potential-cases.html">notes on potential cases</a>.</p>
<p>Set up a placeholder document for <a href="../notes/methodology-notes.html">notes on methodological concerns</a>.</p>
<p>Met with David for our bi-weekly check-in (meeting notes are private, at least for now). I was also given access to the lab’s private git server but haven’t really had much of a chance to explore what it’s being used for or devise my own plans to make use of it.</p>
<p>Worked extensively on the ethics protocol. David and I went back and forth deciding on whether this was necessary, given how the project is based on his grant which already has IRB approval. But it’s better to play it safe than sorry, especially when it’s necessary to obtain informed consent. So to this end, I revised the research protocol and responses to the ethics form, and I also drafted an informed consent document. I’ll share all these things once the whole package is put together (probably in a week or two), but my responses to the ethics form already appears on the <a href="../ethics-protocol.html">ethics protocol</a> page.</p>
<p>I simplified the way private documents are handled in the quarto project and git respository. May still need to so some fiddling, especially for draft blog posts and notes.</p>
<p>I started drafting a blog post about the potential use of AI/LLMs in my research. Stay tuned.</p>
<p>On a related note, I watched this recent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9nAFiF89D6o">video about the use of LLMs in qualitative data analysis</a>, which did not prompt me to draft the post but which is well-timed, nevertheless.</p>
<p>I worked a bit more on the <a href="../data-management.html">data management plan</a>, which prompted me to think more about which QDA software I’ll use. I started filling in a university form to use cloud services provided by MaxQDA, but stumbled upon <a href="https://github.com/cproctor/qualitative-coding/">qualitative-coding</a> (abbreviated as qc), an open source CLI-based QDA system. It represents a very innovative approach to QDA rooted in <a href="https://www.cs.cmu.edu/link/research-notebook-computational-thinking-what-and-why">computational thinking</a> and <a href="https://plain-text.co/">plain text social science</a>, while also remaining true to the core tenets and purpose of QDA, <a href="https://doi.org/10.46743/2160-3715/2018.3096">which make it unique and difficult to design software for</a>. If this is the sort of thing that appeals to you, I highly recommend you read the <a href="https://qualitative-coding.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">docs</a>.</p>
<p>I had a bit of trouble installing it and getting it running, but I met remotely with <a href="https://chrisproctor.net/">Chris Proctor</a>, who develops the tool through his work at the <a href="https://computationalliteracies.net/">Computational Literacies Lab</a>, based in the Department of Learning and Instruction at University at Buffalo (SUNY). He helped me resolve some issues, gave me a guided tour of the system and we just talked about the overall state of qualitative data analysis and its tooling. I don’t really have the capacity right now to post everything he showed me but I will definitely be posting about my experiences tinkering around with qc in the coming weeks.</p>
<p>Similarly, <a href="https://archaeo.social/@zackbatist/113821982780508126">I asked on Mastodon</a> about whether there are any tools that might support automatic generation of transcripts that include support for specialized notation. A few linguists and conversation analysis scholars responded with recommendations to use <a href="https://sites.tufts.edu/hilab/gailbot/">GailBot</a>, and with discussion about the tool’s capabilities and limitations. I requested access to the software but haven’t heard back from the dev team yet. I also created a thread on the <a href="https://github.com/ggerganov/whisper.cpp/discussions/2732">whisper github repo</a>, which I now realize it a bit of a naive place to put it, and it hasn’t yet gotten any responses.</p>
<p>I attended a talk from the epidemiology seminar series, which went wayyyy over my head.</p>
<p>Did my usual amount of engagement on masotodon, I suppose. And I continued to make new friends in the department too :)</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>week notes</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/weeknotes-2025-W03.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reflection on first team meeting</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-first-team-meeting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Last week (2024/12/04) I finally met with David Buckeridge, Tanya Murphy and Aklil Noza in person. The meeting was meant to convey my vision for the project to the whole team, to align perspectives, and to articulate how this will actually work in practice.</p>
<p>The gist is that I will be investigating the role of social and cultural factors in data-sharing initiatives such as CITF and other Maelstrom-affiliated projects, and how these relate to, overlap with, or conflict with technical and institutional/administrative factors. To be clear, these are all very important aspects of data-sharing, but we generally recognized that the social and cultural aspects are under-explored relative to their impact.</p>
<p>We briefly talked about how we will go about selecting cases, and I emphasized the importance of strategic case selection. This also involves carefully articulating the project’s goals so that the cases will complement them. We agreed that the dataset will likely comprise between 12-15 interviews of around 60-90 minutes in length with representatives from 4-5 cases (one of them being CITF), in addition to representatives of the Maelstrom team. Maelstrom will serve as a “fixed point” that limits the scope of the cases’ breadth and ensures that participants have a common frame of reference. It also potentially allows me to “offload” or “consolidate” reference to technical and administrative aspects of data-sharing through targeted interviews with Maelstrom personnel, instead of dealing with those things with the representatives for each case.</p>
<p>We discussed timelines and overlap with Aklil’s work, which will be more concerned with focus groups with CITF databank users. There is definitely overlap with the emphasis of my own work and we will coordinate data collection to enhance the potential for analytical alignment.</p>
<p>After the meeting I chatted with Tanya and Aklil who helped familiarize me with the bigger-picture theoretical discourse and tensions in epidemiology. Much of it seemed familiar since these concerns are common across disciplines, but I still need to read more to concretize my understanding. Tanya recommended I read the “Baby Rothman” which is a condensed version of a very long-lived textbook in this field, among a few other papers she sent me.</p>
<p>Overall, this meeting got me really excited about this project :)</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meeting notes</category>
  <category>general thoughts</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-first-team-meeting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hello World!</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-hello-world.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Welcome to the website for my CITF Postdoc! This will serve as a hub for documenting and sharing my work. I decided to do this as a way of managing and sharing always-updated drafts of research protocols with my supervisor and team members, but it is also generally useful for keeping my thoughts organized. I will also use this blog section to write my thoughts as the project progresses.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>introduction</category>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-hello-world.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
