<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>CITF-Postdoc</title>
<link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Reflection on first team meeting</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-first-team-meeting/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Last week (2024/12/04) I finally met with David Buckeridge, Tanya Murphy and Aklil Noza in person. The meeting was meant to convey my vision for the project to the whole team, to align perspectives, and to articulate how this will actually work in practice.</p>
<p>The gist is that I will be investigating the role of social and cultural factors in data-sharing initiatives such as CITF and other Maelstrom-affiliated projects, and how these relate to, overlap with, or conflict with technical and institutional/administrative factors. To be clear, these are all very important aspects of data-sharing, but we generally recognized that the social and cultural aspects are under-explored relative to their impact.</p>
<p>We briefly talked about how we will go about selecting cases, and I emphasized the importance of strategic case selection. This also involves carefully articulating the project’s goals so that the cases will complement them. We agreed that the dataset will likely comprise between 12-15 interviews of around 60-90 minutes in length with representatives from 4-5 cases (one of them being CITF), in addition to representatives of the Maelstrom team. Maelstrom will serve as a “fixed point” that limits the scope of the cases’ breadth and ensures that participants have a common frame of reference. It also potentially allows me to “offload” or “consolidate” reference to technical and administrative aspects of data-sharing through targeted interviews with Maelstrom personnel, instead of dealing with those things with the representatives for each case.</p>
<p>We discussed timelines and overlap with Aklil’s work, which will be more concerned with focus groups with CITF databank users. There is definitely overlap with the emphasis of my own work and we will coordinate data collection to enhance the potential for analytical alignment.</p>
<p>After the meeting I chatted with Tanya and Aklil who helped familiarize me with the bigger-picture theoretical discourse and tensions in epidemiology. Much of it seemed familiar since these concerns are common across disciplines, but I still need to read more to concretize my understanding. Tanya recommended I read the “Baby Rothman” which is a condensed version of a very long-lived textbook in this field, among a few other papers she sent me.</p>
<p>Overall, this meeting got me really excited about this project :)</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meeting notes</category>
  <category>general thoughts</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-first-team-meeting/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hello World!</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-hello-world/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Welcome to the website for my CITF Postdoc! This will serve as a hub for documenting and sharing my work. I decided to do this as a way of managing and sharing always-updated drafts of research protocols with my supervisor and team members, but it is also generally useful for keeping my thoughts organized. I will also use this blog section to write my thoughts as the project progresses.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>introduction</category>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-09-hello-world/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Technical specs for this website</title>
  <link>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-11-technical-specs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I am using this website as a way to help organize and share key documents and resources. The research protocols are in flux at this stage in the project’s development, and this will make it easier to distribute up-to-date drafts with partners, while simultaneously enhancing transparency.</p>
<p>This post outlines the technical specifications for this website and outlines a roadmap for its further development. It will therefore be continually updated as the site evolves.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I initially created this website using Hugo. You can find an older version of this post reflecting that setup here: <a href="https://github.com/zackbatist/CITF-Postdoc/commit/2346852df7224ca18eff65c0f34335cc6245a78a">#2346852</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="fundamentals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fundamentals">Fundamentals</h2>
<p>This website is based on Quarto, a platform for writing and publishing scientific and technical writing. I had started off using Hugo, but there were too many limitations that Quarto was able to accomodate. I had used quarto before but without fully understanding it, and now I am starting to see its elegance.</p>
<p>The site is hosted on GitHub Pages using a CI workflow to automatically generate the site files upon changes being pushed to the repo. The repo is located at https://github.com/zackbatist/CITF-Postdoc, though I’m making an effort to ensure that the site can be ported to another hosting provider if necessary.</p>
</section>
<section id="generating-pdfs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="generating-pdfs">Generating PDFs</h2>
<p>As an avid user, I do not really want to abandon PDFs entirely. Thankfully, Quarto allows me to pass the markdown through a rendering engine and <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/output-formats/html-multi-format.html">generate outputs in different formats</a> with ease. I relied on this guide for assistance with this:</p>
<p>These PDFs will be tracked with git and I’ll configure a latex template to generate timestamps and references to their corresponding web versions.</p>
</section>
<section id="archiving-and-version-control" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="archiving-and-version-control">Archiving and Version Control</h2>
<p>Every change is tracked using git. However I would also like to find a way to archive each research protocol in Zenodo so that they can be assigned stable DOIs and detailed metadata, which will make them easier to reference.</p>
<p>I do not want to rely on Zenodo’s GitHub integration for two reasons: 1) I want this to be as platform-agnostic as possible, and 2) that system relies on GitHub’s release system which operates on the level of the whole repository rather than specific files. I might be able to write a custom CI workflow to archive specific files to Zenodo using their API. However, I want to be able to toggle this option, rather than have it occur for every single detected change. Maybe I can accomplish this by pushing the changes that I want to archive to a dedicated branch that the CI workflow is configured to operate on. Or it might be easier to simply do this manually, since I’m not sure I will be using it that often anyway.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>website</category>
  <guid>https://zackbatist.info/CITF-Postdoc/posts/2024-12-11-technical-specs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 18:27:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
